<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="appeals-process">
   <title>Appeals Process</title>
   <para>
      While the CDI TCK is rigourous about enforcing an implementation's
      conformance to the JSR-299 specification, it's reasonable to assume that
      an implementor may discover new and/or better ways to validate the
      assertions. This chapter covers the appeals process, defined by the
      Specification Lead, Red Hat Middleware LLC., which allows implementors of
      the JSR-299 specification to challenge one or more tests defined by the
      CDI TCK.
   </para>
   <para>
      The appeals process identifies who can make challenges to the TCK, what
      challenges to the TCK may be submitted, how these challenges are
      submitted, how and by whom challenges are addressed and how accepted
      challenges to the TCK are managed.
   </para>
   <para>
      Following the recent adoption of transparency in the JCP, implementors
      are encouraged to make their appeals public, which this process
      facilitates. The JCP community should recognize that issue reports are a
      central aspect of any good software and it's only natural to point out
      shortcomings and strive to make improvements. Despite this good faith,
      not all implementors will be comfortable with a public appeals process.
      Instructions about how to make a private appeal are therefore provided.
   </para>
   <section>
      <title>Who can make challenges to the TCK?</title>
      <para>
         Any implementor may submit an appeal to challenge one or more tests in
         the CDI TCK. In fact, members of the JSR-299 Expert Group (EG) encourage
         this level of participation.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>What challenges to the TCK may be submitted?</title>
      <para>
         Any test case (e.g., <literal>@Artifact</literal> class,
         <literal>@Test</literal> method), test case configuration (e.g.,
         beans.xml), test beans, annotations and other resources may be
         challenged by an appeal.
      </para>
      <para>
         What is generally not challengable are the assertions made by the
         specification. The specification document is controlled by a separate
         process and challenges to it should be handled through the JSR-299 EG
         by sending an e-mail to <ulink
         url="mailto:jsr299-comments@jcp.org">jsr299-comments@jcp.org</ulink>.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>How these challenges are submitted?</title>
      <para>
         To submit a challenge, a new issue should be created in the <ulink
         url="https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/CDITCK">CDITCK project</ulink>
         of the JBoss JIRA using the Issue Type: Bug. The appellant should
         complete the Summary, Component (TCK Appeal), Environment and
         Description Field only. Any communication regarding the issue should
         be pursed in the comments of the filed issue for accurate record. 
      </para>
      <para>
         To submit an issue in the JBoss JIRA, you must have a (free) JBoss.com
         member account. You can create a member account using the <ulink
         url="http://www.jboss.org/index.html?op=checkage&amp;module=user">on-line
         registration</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
         If you wish to make a private challenge, you should follow the above
         procedure, setting the Security Level to Private. Only the issue
         reporter, TCK Project Lead and designates will be able to view the 
         issue.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>How and by whom challenges are addressed?</title>
      <para>
         The challenges will be addressed in a timely fashion by the CDI TCK
         Project Lead, as designated by Specification Lead, Red Hat Middleware
         LLC. or his/her designate. The appellant can also monitor the process
         by following the issue report filed in the <ulink
         url="https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/WBTCK">WBTCK project</ulink>
         of the JBoss JIRA.
      </para>
      <para>
         The current TCK Project Lead is listed on the <ulink
         url="https://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/CDITCK">CDITCK Project Summary
         Page</ulink> on the JBoss JIRA.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>How accepted challenges to the TCK are managed?</title>
      <para>
         Accepted challenges will be acknowledged via the filed issue's comment
         section. Communication between the CDI TCK Project Lead and the
         appellant will take place via the issue comments. The issue's status
         will be set to "Resolved" when the TCK project lead believes the issue
         to be resolved. The appellant should, within 30 days, either close the
         issue if they agree, or reopen the issue if they do not believe the
         issue to be resolved.
      </para>
      <para>
         Resolved issue not addressed for 30 days will be closed by the TCK
         Project Lead. If the TCK Project Lead and appellant are unable to
         agree on the issue resolution, it will be referred to the JSR-299
         specification lead or his/her designate.
      </para>
      <para>
         Periodically, an updated TCK will be released containing tests altered
         due to challenges. No new tests will be added. Implementations are 
         required to pass the updated TCK. This release stream is named 1.0.z where
         z will be incremented.
      </para>
      <para>
         Additionally, new tests will be added to the TCK improving coverage of the
         specification. We encourage implementations to pass this TCK, however it is
         not required. This release stream is named 1.y.z where y > 0.
      </para>
   </section>
</chapter>
