<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<preface id="book-preface">
   <title>Preface</title>

   <para>
      This guide describes how to download, install, configure, and run the
      Technology Compatibility Kit (TCK) used to verify the compatibility of an
      implementation of the JSR-299: Context and Dependency Injection for Java
      EE (CDI) specification.
   </para>
   <para>
      The CDI TCK is built atop the JBoss Test Harness, a portable and
      configurable automated test suite for authoring unit and integration tests
      in a Java EE environment. The CDI TCK 1.0.0 uses the JBoss Test Harness
      version 1.0.0 to execute the test suite.
   </para>

   <para>
      The CDI TCK is provide under the
      <ulink url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">Apache Public License 2.0</ulink>.
   </para>

   <section id="target-audience">
      <title>Who Should Use This Book</title>
      <para>
         This guide is for implementors of the Context and Dependency
         Injection
         for Java EE 1.0 technology to assist in running the test
         suite
         that verifies the compatibility of their implementation.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section id="before-reading">
      <title>Before You Read This Book</title>

      <para>
         Before reading this guide, you should familiarize yourself with the
         Java EE programming model, specifically the Enterprise JavaBeans (EJB)
         3.0 and the Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE 1.0
         specifications. A good resource for the Java EE programming model is
         the
         <ulink url="http://jcp.org">JCP</ulink>
         web site.
      </para>
      <para>
         The CDI TCK is based on the Context and Dependency Injection for Java
         EE technology specification 1.0 (JSR-299). Information about the
         specification, including links to the specification documents, can be
         found on the
         <ulink url="http://jcp.org/en/jsr/detail?id=299">JSR-299 JCP page</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
         Before running the tests in the CDI TCK, read and become
         familiar
         with the JBoss Test Harness Reference Guide (pending), which
         describes
         how the test harness functions.
      </para>

   </section>
   <section id="book-organization">

      <title>How This Book Is Organized</title>
      <para>
         If you are running the CDI TCK for the first time, read
         <xref linkend="introduction" />
         and
         <xref linkend="test-harness-introduction" />
         completely for the necessary background information about the TCK and
         the JBoss Test Harness, respectively. Once you have reviewed that
         material, perform the steps outlined in the remaining chapters.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="introduction" />
               gives an overview of the principles that apply generally to all
               Technology Compatibility Kits (TCKs), outlines the appeals
               process and describes the CDI TCK architecture and components. It
               also includes a broad overview of how the TCK is executed and
               lists the platforms on which the TCK has been tested and
               verified.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="appeals-process" />
               explains the process to be followed by an implementor should they
               wish to challenge any test in the TCK.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="installation" />
               explains where to obtain the required software for the CDI TCK
               and how to install it. It covers both the primary TCK components
               as well as tools useful for troubleshooting tests.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="configuration" />
               details the configuration of the JBoss Test Harness, how to
               create a TCK runner for the TCK test suite and the mechanics of
               how an in-container test is conducted.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="reporting" />
               explains the test reports that are generated by the TCK test
               suite and introduces the TCK audit report as a tool for measuring
               the completeness of the TCK in testing the JSR-299 specification
               and in understanding how testcases relate to the specification.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="executing" />
               documents how the TCK test suite is executed. It covers both
               modes supported by the TCK, standalone and in-container, and
               shows how to dump the generated test artifacts to disk.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="eclipse-running" />
               shows how to run individual tests in Eclipse and advises the best
               way to setup your Eclipse workspace for running the tests.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="eclipse-debugging" />
               builds on
               <xref linkend="eclipse-running" />
               by detailing how to debug individual tests in Eclipse.
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <xref linkend="test-harness" />
               includes excerpts from the JBoss Test Harness Reference Guide.
               How to configure the JBoss Test Harness as it relates to the CDI
               TCK is presented in
               <xref linkend="configuration" />.
               However, to aid in debugging or configuring the TCK in your
               environment, you may want to read in more detail how to use the
               JBoss Test Harness.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </section>
<!--
vim: ts=3:sw=3:tw=80:set expandtab
-->
</preface>
