<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="configuration">
   <title>Configuration</title>
   <para>
      This chapter lays out how to configure the TCK Harness by specifying
      the SPI implementation classes, defining the target container connection
      information, and various other switches. You then learn how to setup a TCK
      runner project that executes the the TCK test suite, putting these
      settings into practice. Finally, a detailed account of how the JBoss Test
      Harness negotiates the execution of the tests in the container is given.
   </para>

   <para>
      This chapter does not discuss in detail how to use the TCK in standalone
      mode. The JBoss Test Harness guide provides more on running in standalone
      mode.
   </para>
   <section id="tck-harness-properties">
      <title>TCK Harness Properties</title>
      <para>
         The JBoss Test Harness allows the test suite to be launched in a
         pluggable fashion. In order to execute the TCK, the JBoss Test Harness
         must be configured by specifying implementations of the test launcher
         and container APIs.
      </para>
      <para>
         System properties and/or the resource
         <code>META-INF/jboss-test-harness.properties</code>,
         a Java properties file, are used to configure the JBoss Test Harness.
         You can read more about configuring the JBoss Test Harness in
         <xref linkend="test-harness-properties" />.
      </para>
      <para>
         You should set the following properties:
      </para>
      <table frame="all">
         <title>Required JBoss Test Harness Configuration Properties</title>
         <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="property" colwidth="5*" />
            <colspec colnum="2" colname="description" colwidth="2*" />
            <thead>
               <row>
                  <entry>Property = Required/Example Value</entry>
                  <entry>Description</entry>
               </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <literal>org.jboss.testharness.libraryDirectory=/path/to/extra/libraries
                     </literal>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     Directory containing extra JARs you want placed in
                     artifact library directory such as the porting package
                     implementation.
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <literal>org.jboss.testharness.standalone=false</literal>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     You must run the tests in-container to pass the TCK
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <literal>org.jboss.testharness.runIntegrationTests=true
                     </literal>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     You must run the integration tests to pass the TCK
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <literal>org.jboss.testharness.spi.Containers=com.acme.AcmeContainer
                     </literal>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     The container implementation for deploying and
                     executing
                     in-container tests. See
                     <xref linkend="deployment-api-contributions" />
                  </entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>
                     <literal>org.jboss.testharness.api.TestLauncher=org.jboss.testharness.impl.runner.servlet.ServletTestLauncher
                     </literal>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                     You should use the
                     <literal>ServletTestLauncher</literal>
                     for Java EE 6 and Java EE 6 Web Profile.
                  </entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
         To run the full TCK you must additionally implement
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.spi.Containers</literal>,
         which handles deploying the test artifact to the container. An
         implementations of this API is already available for JBoss AS 5.2.
         Therefore, you only need to implement this part of the porting package
         if you wish to use another container.
      </para>
      <note id="deployment-api-contributions">
         <para>
            Red Hat Middleware LLC encourages CDI implementators to
            contribute JBoss Test Harness Deployment API implementations for
            other containers under the ASL license. Please contact the CDI TCK
            lead. 
         </para>
      </note>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>The Porting Package</title>
      <para>
         The CDI TCK relies on an implementation of the porting package to
         function. The porting package can be divided into two parts. The first
         part is comprised of extensions to the CDI SPIs to allow testing of a
         container. The second part must implement the JBoss Test Harness
         artifact deployment APIs for deploying artifacts to the Java EE
         container.
      </para>
      <para>
         As mentioned earlier, there are times when the tests need to tap
         directly into the CDI implementation to manipulate behavior or verify
         results. The porting package includes a set of SPIs that provide the
         TCK this level of access without tying the tests to a given
         implementation.
      </para>
      <para>
         The four SPI classes in the CDI TCK are as follows:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <literal>org.jboss.jsr299.tck.spi.Beans</literal>
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <literal>org.jboss.jsr299.tck.spi.Contexts</literal>
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <literal>org.jboss.jsr299.tck.spi.EL</literal>
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <literal>org.jboss.jsr299.tck.spi.Managers</literal>
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
         Please consult the JavaDoc for these interfaces for the implementation
         requirements.
      </para>

   </section>
   
   <section>
      <title>Using the CDI TCK with the Java EE Web Profile</title>
      <para>
         You can configure the CDI TCK to just run tests appropriate to the Java EE
         Web Profile by adding the <literal>WebProfileMethodSelector</literal> to
         TestNG XML configuration file:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<method-selectors>
   <method-selector>
      <selector-class name="org.jboss.jsr299.tck.impl.WebProfileMethodSelector" />
   </method-selector>
</method-selectors>]]></programlisting>
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Configuring TestNG to execute the TCK</title>
      <para>
         The JBoss Test Harness is built atop TestNG, and it's TestNG that is
         responsible for selecting the tests to execute, the order of
         execution, and reporting the results. Detailed TestNG documentation
         can be found at <ulink
         url="http://testng.org/doc/documentation-main.html">testng.org</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
         The
         <literal>tck-tests.xml</literal>
         artifact provided in the TCK distribution must be run by TestNG 5.9
         (described by the TestNG documentation as "with a
         <literal>testng.xml</literal>
         file") unmodified for an implementation to pass the TCK. This file also
         allows tests to be excluded from a run:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<suite name="JSR-299 TCK" verbose="2">
   <test name="JSR-299 TCK">
      ...
      <classes>
         <class name="org.jboss.jsr299.tck.tests.context.application.ApplicationContextTest">
            <methods>
               <exclude name="testApplicationScopeActiveDuringServiceMethod"/>
            </methods>
         </class>
      </classes>
      ...
   </test>
</suite>]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         TestNG provides extensive reporting information. Depending on the
         build tool or IDE you use, the reporting will take a different format.
         Please consult the TestNG documentation and the tool documentation for
         more information.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Configuring your build environment to execute the TCK</title>
      <para>
         It's beyond the scope of this guide to describe in how to set up your
         build environment to run the TCK. The JBoss Test Harness guide
         describes how Weld uses Maven 2 to execute the CDI TCK. See
         <xref linkend="test-suite-runner" />. The TestNG documentation provides
         extensive information on launching TestNG using the Java, Ant, Eclipse
         or IntellJ IDEA.
      </para>

   </section>
   
   <section>
      <title>Configuring your application server to execute the TCK</title>
      <para>
         The TCK makes use of the Java 1.4 keyword <literal>assert</literal>; you
         must ensure that the JVM used to run the application server is started
         with assertions enabled. See 
         <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/guide/lang/assert.html#enable-disable">Programming With Assertions</ulink>
         for more information on how to enable assertions.
      </para>
   </section>
<!--
vim: ts=3:sw=3:tw=80:set expandtab
-->
</chapter>
