<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="eclipse-running">
   <title>Running Tests in Eclipse</title>
   <para>
      This chapter explains how to run individual tests using the Eclipse
      TestNG plugin. It covers running non-integration tests in standalone mode
      and integration tests (as well as non-integration tests) in in-container
      mode. You should be able to use the lessons learned here to debug tests in
      an alternate IDE as well.
   </para>
   <section>
      <title>Leveraging Eclipse's plugin ecosystem</title>
      <para>
         Using an existing test harness (TestNG) allows the tests to be executed
         and debugged in an Integrated Development Environment (IDE) using
         available plugins. Using an IDE is also the easiest way to execute a
         test class in isolation.

      </para>
      <para>
         The TCK can be executed in any IDE for which there is a TestNG plugin
         available. Running a test from the CDI TCK test suite using the Eclipse
         TestNG plugin is almost as simple as running any other TestNG test. You
         can also use the plugin to debug a test, which is described in the next
         chapter.
      </para>
      <para>
         Before running a test from the TCK test suite in Eclipse, you must have
         the Eclipse <ulink url="http://testng.org">TestNG plugin</ulink> and
         either the m2eclipse plugin or an Eclipse project generated use the
         Maven 2 Eclipse plugin (<literal>maven-eclipse-plugin</literal>). Refer
         to <xref linkend="eclipse-plugins" /> for more information on these
         plugins.
      </para>

      <para>
         With the m2eclipse plugin installed, Eclipse should recognize the
         CDI TCK projects as valid Eclipse projects (or any Weld project
         for that matter). Import them into the Eclipse workspace at this time.
         You should also import the Weld projects if you want to debug into
         that code, which is covered later.
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>
            If you choose to use the Maven 2 Eclipse plugin
            (<literal>maven-eclipse-plugin</literal>), you should execute the
            plugin in both the tck and weld projects:
         </para>
         <programlisting><![CDATA[cd tck
mvn clean eclipse:clean eclipse:eclipse -DdownloadSources -DdownloadJavadocs
cd ../weld
mvn clean eclipse:clean eclipse:eclipse -DdownloadSources -DdownloadJavadocs]]></programlisting>
      </note>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Readying the Eclipse workspace</title>
      <para>
         When setting up your Ecilpse workspace, we recommended creating three
         workings sets:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">Weld</emphasis> - Groups the CDI API
               and the CDI RI (i.e., Weld) projects
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">CDI TCK</emphasis> - Groups the CDI TCK
               API and the test suite projects
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <emphasis role="bold">Weld JBoss TCK Runner</emphasis> -
               Groups the porting package implementation and TCK runner projects
               that are configured to certify Weld deployed on JBoss AS 5.2
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para> 
         The dependencies between the projects will either be established
         automatically by the m2eclipse plugin, based on the dependency
         information in the pom.xml files, or as generated by the <literal>mvn
         eclipse:eclipse</literal> command.
      </para>
      <para>
         Your workspace should appear as follows:
      </para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[Weld
  cdi-api
  weld-api
  weld-core
  weld-core-test
  weld-logging
  weld-parent
  weld-spi
  weld-version-matrix
CDI TCK
  jsr299-tck-api
  jsr299-tck-impl
  jsr299-tck-parent
Weld JBoss TCK Runner
  weld-jboss-tck-runner
  weld-porting-package]]></programlisting>
      <para>
         The tests in the TCK test suite are located in the jsr299-tck-impl
         project. You'll be working within this project in Eclipse when you are
         developing tests. However, as you learned earlier, there are no references
         to a CDI implementation in the TCK. So how can you execute an
         individual test in Eclipse? The secret is that you need to establish a
         link in Eclipse (not in Maven) between the jsr299-tck-impl project and
         your TCK runner project, which in this case is
         weld-jboss-tck-runner (the project in the jboss-tck-runner
         directory).
      </para>
      <para>
         Here are the steps to establish the link:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Right click on the jsr299-tck-impl project
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select Build Path &gt; Configure Build Path...
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click on the Projects tab
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the Add... button on the right
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Check the TCK runner project (e.g., weld-jboss-tck-runner)
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the OK button on the Required Project Selection dialog
               window
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the OK button on the Java Build Path window
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
         Of course, the weld-jboss-tck-runner also depends on the
         jsr299-tck-impl at runtime (so it can actually find the tests to
         execute). But Eclipse doesn't distinguish between build-time and
         runtime dependencies. As a result, we've created a circular dependency
         between the projects. In all likelihood, Eclipse will struggle (if not
         fail) to compile one or more projects. How can we break this cycle?
      </para>
      <para>
         As it turns out, the TCK runner doesn't need to access the tests to
         build. It only needs its classes, configurations and other dependenices
         at runtime (when the TestNG plugin executes). Therefore, we can remove
         the TCK runner's dependence on the jsr299-tck-impl project by following
         these steps:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Right click on the weld-jboss-tck-runner project
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select Build Path &gt; Configure Build Path...
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click on the Projects tab
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select the TCK tests project (jsr299-tck-impl)
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the Remove button on the right
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the OK button on the Java Build Path window
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
         You are now ready to execute an individual test class (or artifact).
         Let's start with a test artifact capable of running in standalone mode.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section id="eclipse-standalone">
      <title>Running a test in standalone mode</title>
      <para>
         A standalone test artifact is a class which extends
         <literal>AbstractJSR299Test</literal>, is annotated with
         <literal>@Artifact</literal>, but is <emphasis
         role="italic">not</emphasis> annotated with
         <literal>@IntegrationTest</literal>. Select a standalone test artifact
         and open it in the Eclipse editor.  Now right click in the editor view
         and select Run As &gt; TestNG Test. The TestNG view should pop out and
         you should see all the tests in that artifact pass (if all goes well).
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>
            If the TCK complains that there is a property missing, close all
            the projects, open them again, and rebuild. The m2eclipse plugin can
            be finicky getting everything built correctly the first time.
         </para>
      </note>
      <para>
         So far you have executed a test in standalone mode. That's not
         sufficient to pass the TCK. The test must be executed using 
         in-container mode. Using in-container mode is also the only way to
         execute a test annotated with <literal>@IntegrationTest</literal>
         (that's what the annotation means) as it requires container resources.
      </para>
      <para>
         Let's see what has to be done to execute an integration test. This
         will result in the artifact being deployed to the container, which is
         JBoss AS 5.2 if you are using the JBoss TCK runner.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section id="eclipse-in-container">
      <title>Running integration tests</title>
      <para>
         As you have learned, the JBoss test harness determines how to behave
         based on the values of numerous system properties or properties defined
         in META-INF/jboss-test-harness.properties classpath resources. If the
         property named
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.standalone</literal>
         is not defined, the harness assumes that the test is to be run in
         standalone mode. In order to run the tests in the container, you need
         to add a properties file to the classpath that sets the standalone
         property to false and provides values for other properties required to
         run an in-container test.
      </para>
      <para>
         The JBoss TCK runner project conveniently provides the properties file
         src/test/debug-resources/META-INF/jboss-test-harness.properties that
         contains all of the necessary properties for in-container testing in
         Eclipse. Assuming you followed the directory structure recommended in
         <xref linkend="tck-environment"/>, you are good to go. Otherwise, you
         may have to tune the
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.container.extraConfigurationDir</literal> and
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.libraryDirectory</literal> properties to
         point to the relative location of the related projects. The properties
         should be defined as follows:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <literal>org.jboss.testharness.container.extraConfigurationDir
               </literal>
               - the relative path from the jboss-tck-impl project to a
               directory that contains a build.properties or
               local.build.properties file defining the location of a JBoss AS
               5.2 installation in the
               <literal>jboss.home</literal>
               property
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               <literal>org.jboss.testharness.libraryDirectory</literal>
               - the relative path from the jboss-tck-impl project to the
               target/dependency/lib directory in the TCK runner project.
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
         The other properties in that file are defined as follows:
      </para>
      <programlisting>org.jboss.testharness.standalone=false
orjboss.testharness.container.forceRestart=false
orjboss.testharness.runIntegrationTests=true</programlisting>
      <para>
         You're now ready to execute an integration test. Select an integration
         test (a class that extends <literal>AbstractJSR299Test</literal> and is
         annotated with both <literal>@Artifact</literal> and
         <literal>@IntegrationTest</literal>) and open it in your Eclipse
         editor. Follow these steps to execute the class with the TestNG plugin:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Right click in the editor view and select Run As &gt; TestNG Test
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Observe the test fail because of missing dependencies
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select the Run &gt; Run Configurations... menu from the main
               menubar
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select the name of the test class under the TestNG category
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select the Classpath tab
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select User Entries in the tree
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the Advanced... button on the right
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select Add Folders and click the OK button
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select the weld-jboss-tck-runner/src/test/debug-resources
               folder
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the OK button on the Folder Selection dialog window
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click on the weld-jboss-tck-runner entry
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Move the weld-jboss-tck-runner to the first entry using
               the Up button
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the Run button on the Run Configurations dialog window
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
         When you run the test this time, it should pass. If you get a
         failure that the container (e.g., JBoss AS 5.2) must be run with
         assertions enabled, you need to stop the container and start it with
         the -ea flag (or just leave it stopped and the test will start it
         appropriately). 
      </para>
      <para>
         You can simply right click and select Run As &gt; TestNG Test for
         all subsequent runs for the reason cited earlier, the run configuration
         for a class is retained indefinitely.
      </para>
      <para>
         Alternatively, you can configure TestNG to execute all tests
         in-container by default by adding the properties file in the
         debug-resources folder to the project's classpath as follows:
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Right click on the jsr299-tck-impl project
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Select Build Path &gt; Configure Build Path...
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click on the Libraries tab
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the Add Class Folder... button on the right
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Check the weld-jboss-tck-runner/src/test/debug-resources
               folder
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the OK button on the Class Folder Selection dialog
               window
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Click the OK button on the Java Build Path window
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
         Now you don't have to do any special configuration per test class.
      </para>
      <para>
         You can stop the individual tests from running in-container by
         reversing the steps above to remove the debug-resources folder from the
         Eclipse classpath. 
      </para>
      <para>
         You have now mastered running the CDI TCK against Weld using
         both Maven 2 and within Eclipse. Now you're likely interested in how to
         debug a test so that you can efficiently investigate test failures.
      </para>
   </section>
<!--
vim: ts=3:sw=3:tw=80:set expandtab
-->
</chapter>
