<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="executing">
   <title>Executing the Test Suite</title>
   <para>
      This chapter explains how to run the TCK on Weld as well as your own
      implementation. The CDI TCK uses the Maven 2 TestNG plugin and the JBoss
      Test Harness to execute the test suite. Learning to execute the test suite
      from Maven 2 is prerequisite knowlege for running the tests in an IDE,
      such as Eclipse.
   </para>
   <section>
      <title>The Test Suite Runner</title>

      <para>
         The test suite is executed by the Maven 2 TestNG plugin during the test
         phase of the Maven 2 life cycle. The execution happens within a TCK
         runner project (as opposed to the TCK project itself). Weld
         includes a TCK runner project that executes the CDI TCK on Weld
         running inside JBoss AS 6.0. To execute the CDI TCK on your own CDI
         implementation, you could modify the TCK runner project included with
         Weld to use your CDI implementation as described in <xref
         linkend="configuration" />.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Running the Tests In Standalone Mode</title>
      <para>
         To execute the TCK test suite against Weld, first switch to the
         jboss-tck-runner directory in the extracted Weld distribution:
      </para>

      <programlisting>cd weld/jboss-tck-runner</programlisting>
      <note>
         <para>
             These instructions assume you have extracted the CDI-related
             software according to the recommendation given in <xref
             linkend="tck-environment"/>.
         </para>
      </note>
      <para>
         Then execute the Maven 2 life cycle through the test phase:
      </para>
      <programlisting>mvn test</programlisting>
      <para>
         Without any command-line flags, the test suite is run in standalone
         mode, which means that any test class with the
         <literal>@org.jboss.testharness.impl.packaging.IntegrationTest
         </literal>
         annotation is skipped. This mode uses the
         <literal>StandaloneContainers</literal>
         SPI to invoke the test artifact within a mock Java EE life cycle and
         capture the results of the test. However, passing the suite in this
         mode is not sufficient to pass the TCK as a whole. The suite must be
         passed while executing using the in-container mode.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Running the Tests In the Container</title>
      <para>
         To execute the test suite using in-container mode with the JBoss TCK
         runner, you first have to setup JBoss AS as described in the 
         <xref linkend="tck-in-jboss-as" /> callout.
      </para>
      <para>
         Then, execute the TCK runner with Maven 2 as follows:
      </para>
      <programlisting>mvn test -Dincontainer</programlisting>
      <para>
         The presence of the <literal>incontainer</literal> property activates a
         Maven 2 profile that assigns the
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.standalone</literal> system property to
         <literal>false</literal> and the
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.runIntegrationTests</literal> system
         property to <literal>true</literal>, hence activating the in-container
         test mode. This time, all the test artifacts in the test suite are
         executed.
      </para>
      <para>
         The in-container profile will also start and stop the application
         server automatically, a feature which the profile activates by setting
         the <literal>org.jboss.testharness.container.forceRestart</literal> to
         <literal>true</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
         The in-container mode uses the <literal>Containers</literal> SPI to
         deploy the test artifact to the container and execute the test in a
         true Java EE life cycle. The JBoss TCK runner has a dependency on the
         library that provides an implementation of this interface for JBoss AS
         6.0.
      </para>
      <para>
         Since in-container tests are executed in a remote JVM, the results of
         the test must be communicated back to the runner over a
         container-supported protocol. The JBoss Test Harness provides
         servlet-based communication over HTTP as described in <xref
         linkend="incontainer-communication" />.
      </para>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Dumping the Test Artifacts</title>
      <para>
         As you have learned, when the test suite is executing using
         in-container mode, each test class is packaged as a deployable artifact
         and deployed to the container. The test is then executed within the
         context of the deployed application. This leaves room for errors in
         packaging. When investigating a test failure, you may find it helpful
         to inspect the artifact after it's generated. The TCK can accommodate
         this type of inspection by "dumping" the generated artifact to disk.
      </para>
      <para>
         The feature just described is activated in the jboss-tck-runner project
         by appending the <literal>dumpArtifacts</literal> command line property
         to the end of the command that invokes the Maven 2 test phase.
      </para>
      <programlisting>mvn test-compile -DdumpArtifacts</programlisting>
      <para>
         The directory where the artifacts get written is configured using the
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.outputDirectory</literal> property. The
         <literal>dumpArtifacts</literal> profile in the jboss-tck-runner
         project sets this value to the relative directory path
         <literal>target/jsr299-artifacts</literal>.
      </para>
      
      <para>
         However, if you are using Ant, you will be pleased to see the
         <literal>lib/</literal>, containing all dependencies required
         to run the TCK - just add every jar to your classpath. Further
         if you are using Weld, and wish to use Weld's implementation of
         the porting package, you should add every jar in <literal>weld/porting-package-lib</literal>
         to your classpath.
      </para>
   </section>
   <!--
vim: ts=3:sw=3:tw=80:set expandtab
-->
</chapter>
