<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="installation">
   <title>Installation</title>
   <para>
      This chapter explains how to obtain the TCK and supporting software and
      provides recommendations for how to install/extract it on your system.
   </para>
   <section>
      <title>Obtaining the Software</title>
      <para>
         You can obtain a release of the CDI TCK project from the from the
         <ulink url="http://seamframework.org/Download">download page</ulink>
         on Seam Framework website. The CDI TCK is distributed as a ZIP file,
         which contains the TCK artifacts (the test suite binary and source,
         porting package API binary and source, the test suite descriptor, the
         audit source and report) in
         <code>/artifacts</code>, the TCK library dependencies in
         <code>/lib</code>
         and documentation in
         <code>/lib</code>.
      </para>
      <para>
         You can also download the currnet source code from
         <ulink url="http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/weld/cdi-tck/trunk">JBoss SVN repository</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
         The TCK project is available in the JBoss Maven 2 repository as
         <code>org.jboss.jsr299.tck:jsr299-tck-impl</code>; the POM defines all
         dependencies required to run the TCK.
      </para>
      <para>
         Executing the TCK requires a Java EE 5 or better runtime environment
         (i.e., application server), to which the test artifacts are deployed
         and the individual tests are invoked. The TCK does not depend on any
         particular Java EE implementation.
      </para>
      <para>
         The JSR-299: Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE 1.0
         reference implementation (RI) project is named Web Beans. You can
         obtain the latest Web Beans release from the
         <ulink url="http://seamframework.org/Download">download page</ulink>
         on Seam Framework website.
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>
            Web Beans is not required for running the CDI TCK, but it can be
            used as a reference for familiarizing yourself with the TCK before
            testing your own CDI implementation.
         </para>
      </note>
      <para>
         Naturally, to execute Java programs, you must have a Java SE runtime
         environment. The TCK requires Java 5 or better, which you can obtain
         from the
         <ulink url="http://java.sun.com">Java Software</ulink>
         website.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section id="tck-environment">
      <title>The TCK Environment</title>

      <para>
         The TCK requires the following two Java runtime environments:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Java 5 or better
            </para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>
               Java EE 5 or better (e.g., JBoss AS 5.x or GlassFish V3)
            </para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
         You should refer to vendor instructions for how to install the
         runtime.
      </para>
      <para>
         The rest of the TCK software can simply be extracted. It's
         recommended that you create a folder named jsr299 to hold all of the
         jsr299-related projects. Then, extract the TCK distribution into a
         subfolder named tck. If you have downloaded the Weld distribution,
         extract it into a sibling folder named weld. The resulting folder
         structure is shown here:
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>
            This layout is assumed through all descriptions in this reference
            guide.
         </para>
      </note>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[jsr299/
   weld/
   tck/]]></programlisting>

      <para>
         Each test class is treated as an individual artifact (hence the
         <literal>@Artifact</literal>
         annotation on the class). All test methods (i.e., methods annotated
         with
         <literal>@Test</literal>)
         in the test class are run in the application, meaning bean discovery
         occurs exactly once per artifact and the same BeanManager is used by
         each test method in the class.
      </para>

      <tip id="tck-in-jboss-as">
         <title>
            Running the TCK against the CDI RI (Web Beans) and JBoss AS
         </title>

         <para>
            Web Beans is built as a modular library, and as such can be
            retro-fitted to Java EE 5 products as required. JBoss AS 5.1 and
            above releases bundle Web Beans. JBoss AS 5.1 also allows you to
            upgrade the Web Beans module to the current release (though some
            functionality may be disabled).
         </para>

         <para>
            To install JBoss AS 5.1 and update to the latest Web Beans
            release: 
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  First, you should download JBoss AS 5.1 from the JBoss AS
                  <ulink url="http://jboss.org/jbossas/downloads">project page</ulink>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Set the
                  <literal>JBOSS_HOME</literal>
                  environment variable to the location of the JBoss AS software.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Change to the weld directory.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Make sure the
                  <literal>jboss.home</literal>
                  property in the local.build.properties file in the jboss-as
                  directory references a JBoss AS 5.1 installation:
               </para>
               <programlisting>jboss.home=/path/to/jboss-as-5.1</programlisting>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Then, run Ant from the jboss-as directory to install the
                  deployer:
               </para>
               <programlisting>ant update</programlisting>
               <para>
                  The libraries needed by the deployer are fetched from the
                  Maven 2 repository on demand.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>
            Web Beans includes a TCK runner that executes the TCK using Web
            Beans as the CDI implementation and JBoss AS as the Java EE runtime.
            To run the tck:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  You need to install Maven. You can find documention on how to
                  install Maven 2 in the
                  <ulink
                     url="http://www.sonatype.com/books/maven-book/reference/installation-sect-maven-install.html">Maven: The Definitive Guide</ulink>
                  book published by Sonatype. Web Beans bundles a copy of Maven
                  in the
                  <code>lib/maven</code>
                  directory.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Next, instruct Maven to run the TCK:
               </para>
               <programlisting><![CDATA[cd jboss-tck-runner
mvn test -Dincontainer]]></programlisting>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  TestNG will report, via Maven, the outcome of the run, and
                  report
                  any failures on the console. Details can be found in
                  <code>target/surefire-reports/TestSuite.txt</code>.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

      </tip>
   </section>
   <section id="eclipse-plugins">
      <title>Eclipse Plugins</title>
      <para>
         Eclipse, or any other IDE, is not required to execute or pass the TCK.
         However an implementor may wish to execute tests in an IDE to aid
         debugging the tests. This section introduces two essential Eclipse
         plugins, TestNG and Maven 2, and points you to resources explaining
         how to install them.
      </para>
      <section id="eclipse-testng-plugin">
         <title>TestNG Plugin</title>
         <para>
            The TCK is built on the JBoss Test Harness, which is in turn built on
            TestNG. Therefore, having the TestNG plugin installed in Eclipse is
            essential. Instructions for using the TestNG update site to add the
            TestNG plugin to Eclipse are provided on the TestNG
            <ulink url="http://testng.org/doc/download.html">download page</ulink>.
            You can find a tutorial that explains how to use the TestNG plugin on
            the TestNG
            <ulink url="http://testng.org/doc/eclipse.html">Eclipse page</ulink>.
         </para>
      </section>
      <section id="m2eclipse-plugin">
         <title>Maven 2 Plugin (m2eclipse)</title>
         <para>
            Another useful plugin is m2eclipse. Both the TCK project and Web Beans
            are use Maven 2. Therefore, to work with these projects in Eclipse, you
            may wish to have native support for Maven 2 projects, which the m2eclipse
            plugin provides. Instructions for using the m2eclipse update site to
            add the m2eclipse plugin to Eclipse are provided on the m2eclipse home
            page. For more, read the m2eclipse
            <ulink url="http://www.sonatype.com/books/m2eclipse-book/reference">reference guide</ulink>.
         </para>
         <para>
            m2eclipse is still a rather young project dealing with a complex
            domain and you may run into problems using it. If that is the case,
            you can alternatively use the Eclipse plugin for Maven 2 to
            generate native Eclipse projects from Maven 2 projects.
         </para>
         <para>
            If you have Maven 2 installed, you have everything you need.  Just
            execute the following command from any Maven 2 project to produce
            the Eclipse project files.
         </para>
         <programlisting>mvn eclipse:eclipse</programlisting>
      </section>
      <para>
         Again, the Eclipse plugins are not required to execute the TCK, but
         can be very helpful when validating an implementation against the TCK
         test suite and especially when using the modules from the Web Beans
         project.
      </para>
   </section>
<!--
vim: ts=3:sw=3:tw=80:set expandtab
-->
</chapter>
