<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="introduction">
   <title>Introduction (CDI TCK)</title>

   <para>
      This chapter explains the purpose of a TCK and identifies the
      foundation elements of the CDI TCK.
   </para>
   <section>
      <title>TCK Primer</title>
      <para>
         A TCK, or Technology Compatibility Kit, is one of the three required
         pieces for any JSR (the other two being the specification document and
         the reference implementation). The TCK is a set of tools and tests to
         verify that an implementation of the technology conforms to the
         specification. The tests are the primary component, but the tools serve
         an equally critical role of providing a framework and/or set of SPIs
         for executing the tests.
      </para>
      <para>
         The tests in the TCK are derived from assertions in the written
         specification document. The assertions are itemized in an XML
         document, where they each get assigned a unique identifier, and
         materialize as a suite of automated tests that collectively validate
         whether an implementation complies with the aforementioned assertions,
         and in turn the specification. For a particular implementation to be
         certified, all of the required tests must pass (i.e., the provided
         test suite must be run unmodified).
      </para>
      <para>
         A TCK is entirely implementation agnostic. Ideally, it should validate
         assertions by consulting the specficiation's public API.  However, when
         the information returned by the public API is not low-level enough to
         validate the assertion, the implementation must be consulted directly.
         In this case, the TCK provides an independent API as part of a porting
         package that enables this transparency. The porting package must be
         implemented for each CDI implementation. Section 1.3.4 introduces the
         porting package and section 4.1 covers the requirements for
         implementing it.
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>
            Sun Microsystems, Inc. will implement the porting package for the
            CDI RI and test the CDI RI on the Java EE Reference Implementation.
         </para>
      </note>
   </section>
   <section>
      <title>Compatibility Testing</title>

      <para>
         The goal of any specification is to eliminate portability problems
         so long as the program which uses the implementation also conforms to
         the rules laid out in the specification.
      </para>
      <para>
         Executing the TCK is a form of compatibility testing. It's important
         to understand that compatibility testing is distinctly different from
         product testing. The TCK is not concerned with robustness, performance
         or ease of use, and therefore cannot vouch for how well an
         implementation meets these criteria. What a TCK can do is to ensure the
         exactness of an implementation as it relates to the specification.
      </para>
      <para>
         Compatibility testing of any feature relies on both a complete
         specification and a complete reference implementation. The reference
         implementation demonstrates how each test can be passed and provides
         additional context to the implementor during development for the
         corresponding assertion.
      </para>

      <section>
         <title>Why Compatibility Is Important</title>
         <para>
            Java platform compatibility is important to different groups
            involved with Java technologies for different reasons:
         </para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Compatibility testing is the means by which the JCP ensures
                  that the Java platform does not become fragmented as it's
                  ported to different operating systems and hardware.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Compatibility testing benefits developers working in the
                  Java programming language, enabling them to write applications
                  once and deploy them across heterogeneous computing
                  environments without porting.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Compatibility testing enables application users to obtain
                  applications from disparate sources and deploy them with
                  confidence.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>Conformance testing benefits Java platform implementors by
                  ensuring the same extent of reliability for all Java platform
                  ports.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para>
            The CDI specification goes to great lengths to ensure that
            programs written for Java EE are compatible and the TCK is rigorous
            about enforcing the rules the specification lays down.
         </para>
      </section>

   </section>

   <section>
      <title>About the CDI TCK</title>

      <para>
         The CDI TCK is designed as a portable, configurable and automated test
         suite for verifying the compatibility of an implementation of the
         JSR-299: Contexts and Dependency Injection for Java EE specification.
         The test suite is built atop TestNG and provides a series of extensions
         that allow runtime packaging and deployment of JEE artifacts for
         in-container testing (JBoss Test Harness).
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>
            The CDI TCK harness is based on the JBoss Test harness, which
            provides most of the aforementioned functionality.
         </para>
      </note>
      <para>
         Each test class in the suite acts as a deployable unit. The
         deployable units, or artifacts, are defined declaratively using
         annotations. The artifact produced can be either a WAR or an EAR.
      </para>
      <para>
         The declarative approach allows many of the tests to be executed in
         a standalone implementation of CDI, accounting for a boast in developer
         productivity. However, an implementation is only valid if all tests
         pass using the in-container execution mode. The standalone mode is
         merely a developer convenience.
      </para>

      <section>
         <title>CDI TCK Specifications and Requirements</title>
         <para>
            This section lists the applicable requirements and specifications
            for the CDI TCK.
         </para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Specification requirements</emphasis>
                  - Software requirements for a CDI implementation are itemized
                  in section 1.2, "Relationship to other specifications" in the
                  CDI specification, with details provided throughout the
                  specification. Generally, the CDI specification targets the
                  Java EE 6 platform and is aligned with its specifications.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Contexts and Dependency Injection for
                     Java EE 1.0 API</emphasis>
                  - The Java API defined in the CDI specification and provided
                  by the reference implementation.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">JBoss Test Harness</emphasis>
                  - The CDI TCK requires version 1.1.0-CR3 of the JBoss Test
                  Harness. The Harness is based on TestNG 5.x 
                  (<ulink url="http://testng.org">http://testng.org</ulink>).
                  You can read more about the harness in
                  <xref linkend="test-harness" />.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Porting Package</emphasis>
                  - An implementation of SPIs that are required for the test
                  suite to run the in-container tests and at times extend the
                  CDI 1.0 API to provide extra information to the TCK.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">TCK Audit Tool</emphasis>
                  - An itemization of the assertions in the specification
                  documents which are cross referenced by the individual tests.
                  Describes how well the TCK covers the specification.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Reference runtime</emphasis>
                  - The designated reference runtimes for compatibility testing
                  of the CDI specification is the Sun Java Platform, Enterprise
                  Edition (Java EE) 6 reference implementation (RI). See details
                  at Java EE 6
                  (<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javaee/6/docs/api/">http://java.sun.com/javaee/6/docs/api/</ulink>).
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">JSR-330</emphasis> - CDI builds on JSR-330,
                  and as such JSR-299 implementations must additionally pass the
                  JSR-330 TCK.
               </para>
               <tip>
                  <para>
                     The TCK distribution includes <literal>weld/porting-package-lib/weld-inject-tck-runner-X.Y.Z-Q-tests.jar</literal>
                     which contains two classes showing how the CDI RI passes the JSR-330
                     TCK. The source for these classes is available from <ulink url="http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/weld/tags/1.0.0-CR2/inject-tck-runner/src/test/java/org/jboss/weld/atinject/tck/" />
                  </para>
               </tip>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>CDI TCK Components</title>
         <para>The CDI TCK includes the following components:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">JBoss Test Harness 1.0.0</emphasis>
                  and related documentation.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">TestNG 5.9</emphasis>, the testing
                  framework on which the JBoss Test Harness is based and which
                  provides the extension points for selecting an executing the
                  tests in the test suite.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Porting Package SPIs</emphasis>
                  - Extensions to the CDI SPIs to allow testing of a
                  container.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">The test suite</emphasis>, which is a
                  collection of TestNG tests, the TestNG test suite descriptor
                  and supplemental resources that configure CDI and other
                  software components.
               </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">The TCK audit</emphasis>
                  is used to list out the assertions identified in the CDI
                  specification. It matches the assertions to testcases in the
                  test suite by unique identifier and produces a coverage report.
               </para>
               <para>
                  The audit document is provided along with the TCK; at least
                  75% of assertions are tested. Each assertion is defined with a
                  reference to a chapter, section and paragraph from the
                  specification document, making it easy for the implementor to
                  locate the language in the specification document that
                  supports the feature being tested.
         </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">TCK documentation</emphasis>
                  accompanied by release notes identifying updates between
                  versions.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <note>
            <para>
               Sun Microsystems, Inc. will implement the porting package for the
               CDI RI and test the CDI RI on the Java EE Reference
               Implementation .
            </para>
         </note>
         <para>The CDI TCK has been tested run on following platforms:</para>
         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  JBoss AS 5.2.0.Beta1 using Sun Java SE 6 on Red Hat Enterprise 
                  Linux 5.2
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
         <para>
            CDI supports Java EE 5, Java EE 6, Java EE 6 Web Profile and the
            Embeddable EJB 3.1. The TCK will execute on any of these runtimes, 
            but is only part of the CTS for Java EE 6 and Java EE 6 Web Profile.
         </para>
      </section>
   </section>
<!--
vim: ts=3:sw=3:tw=80:set expandtab
-->
</chapter>
