<specification xmlns="http://jboss.com/products/weld/tck/audit"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://jboss.com/products/weld/tck/audit"
    name="JSR-318: Interceptors Specification" id="int" version="1.2">

    <section id="1" title="Overview">
    </section>

    <section id="2" title="Interceptor Programming Contract">
    </section>

    <section id="2.1" title="Interceptor Definition">

        <group>
            <text>An interceptor method may be defined on a target class or on an interceptor class associated with the target class.</text>
            <assertion id="aa">
                <text>Interceptor method may be defined on a target class.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="ab">
                <text>Interceptor method may be defined on an interceptor class associated with the target class.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>Any number of interceptor classes may be associated with a target class.</text>
            <note>It's not possible to test all the combinations, we only test few basic scenarios.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c" testable="false">
            <text>An interceptor class must not be |abstract| and must have a |public| no-arg constructor.</text>
            <note>INTERCEPTORS_SPEC-22</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>An around-invoke interceptor method, an around-timeout interceptor method, and lifecycle callback interceptor methods for different lifecycle events may be defined on the same interceptor class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>An interceptor class may have superclasses.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f" testable="false">
            <text>Interceptor methods and interceptor classes may be defined for a class by means of metadata annotations or, optionally, by means of a deployment descriptor.</text>
            <note>Tested in several other sections</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="g" testable="false">
            <text>Interceptors classes may be associated with the target class using either interceptor binding or the |Interceptors| annotation. Typically only one interceptor association type is used for any component.</text>
            <note>Tested in sections 3.3 and 4</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="h" testable="false">
            <text>A deployment descriptor may be used to specify the invocation order of interceptors or to override the order specified in metadata annotations. A deployment descriptor can be optionally used to define default interceptors or to associate interceptors with the target class. The EJB specification requires support for the ejb-jar.xml deployment descriptor and the CDI specification requires supports for the beans.xml deployment descriptor.</text>
        	<note>The ejb-jar.xml deployment descriptor is tested within the EJB TCK. The beans.xml deployment descriptor is tested within the CDI TCK, section 9.4 Interceptor enablement and ordering.</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.2" title="Interceptor Life Cycle">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>The lifecycle of an interceptor instance is the same as that of the target class instance with which it is associated.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>Except as noted below, when the target instance is created, a corresponding interceptor instance is created for each associated interceptor class. These interceptor instances are destroyed if the target instance fails to be created or when it is removed.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>An interceptor instance may be the target of dependency injection. Dependency injection is performed when the interceptor instance is created, using the naming context of the associated target class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>When a |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptor is used, the following rules apply:</text>
            <assertion id="da">
                <text>The |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback is invoked after the dependency injection has been completed on instances of all interceptor classes associated with the target class. Injection of the target component into interceptor instances that are invoked during the |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback is not supported.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="db">
                <text>The target instance is created and its constructor injection is performed, if applicable, when the last interceptor method in the |AroundConstruct| interceptor chain invokes the |InvocationContext.proceed| method. If the |InvocationContext.proceed| method is not invoked by an interceptor method, the target instance will not be created.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="dc">
                <text>The |AroundConstruct| interceptor method can access the constructed instance using the |InvocationContext.getTarget| method after the |InvocationContext.proceed| completes.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="dd">
                <text>Dependency injection on the target instance is not completed until after invocation of all interceptor methods in the |AroundConstruct| interceptor chain complete successfully.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="de">
                <text>The |PostConstruct| lifecycle callback chain for the target instance, if any, will be invoked after the dependency injection has been completed on the target instance.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="df">
                <text>An |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptor method should exercise caution when invoking methods of the target instance since its dependency injection may not have been completed.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>With the exception of |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptors, all interceptor methods, including |PostConstruct| callbacks are invoked after dependency injection has been completed on both the interceptor instances and the target instance.</text>
            <note>If the PostConstruct callback is defined on the interceptor class, this callback it is not invoked when the interceptor instance itself is created.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f">
            <text>|PreDestroy| callbacks, if any, are invoked before the target instance and all interceptor instances associated with it are destroyed.</text>
            <note>If the PreDestroy callback is defined on the interceptor class, it is not invoked when the interceptor instance itself is destroyed.</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.2.1" title="Interceptor Environment">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>An interceptor class shares the enterprise naming context of its associated target class. Annotations and/or XML deployment descriptor elements for dependency injection or for direct JNDI lookup refer to this shared naming context.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>Around-invoke and around-timeout interceptor methods run in the same Java thread as the associated target method.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>It is possible to carry state across multiple interceptor method invocations for a single method invocation or lifecycle callback event in the context data of the |InvocationContext| object. The |InvocationContext| object also provides metadata that enables interceptor methods to control the behavior of the interceptor invocation chain, including whether the next method in the chain is invoked and the values of its parameters and result.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.3" title="InvocationContext">

        <assertion id="a" testable="false">
            <text>The InvocationContext object provides metadata that enables interceptor methods to control the behavior of the invocation chain.</text>
            <note>Statement of intent</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="ba">
            <text>The same |InvocationContext| instance will be passed to each interceptor method for a given target class method or lifecycle event interception. This allows an interceptor to save information in the context data property of the InvocationContext that can be subsequently retrieved in other interceptors as a means to pass contextual data between interceptors. The contextual data is not sharable across separate target class method invocations or lifecycle callback events.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="bb">
            <text>If interceptors are invoked as a result of the invocation on a web service endpoint, the map returned by getContextData() will be the JAX-WS MessageContext.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>The getTarget method returns the associated target instance. For the |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptor method, |getTarget| returns |null| if called before the proceed method returns.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="da">
            <text>The |getTimer| method returns the timer object associated with a timeout method invocation.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="db">
            <text>The |getTimer| method returns |null| for around-invoke methods and lifecycle callback interceptor methods.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="ea">
            <text>The |getMethod| method returns the method of the target class for which the interceptor was invoked.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="eb">
            <text>In a lifecycle callback interceptor for which there is no corresponding lifecycle callback method on the target class or in the |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptor method, getMethod returns |null|.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f">
            <text>The |getParameters| method returns the parameters of the method or constructor invocation. If the |setParameters| method has been called, getParameters returns the values to which the parameters have been set.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>The |setParameters| method modifies the parameters used for the target class method or constructor invocation. Modifying the parameter values does not affect the determination of the method or the constructor that is invoked on the target class. The parameter types must match the types for the target class method or constructor, and the number of parameters supplied must equal the number of parameters on the target class method or constructor, or the |IllegalArgumentException| is thrown.</text>
            <assertion id="ga">
                <text>Test |setParameters| method modifies the parameters used.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="gb">
                <text>Test invalid number of parameters.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="gc">
                <text>Test invalid parameter types.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <group>
            <text>The |proceed| method causes the invocation of the next interceptor method in the chain, or, when called from the last around-invoke or around-timeout interceptor method, the target class method.</text>
            <assertion id="ha">
                <text>Test around-invoke interceptor method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="hb">
                 <text>Test around-timeout interceptor method.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="i">
            <text>For |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptor methods, the invocation of the last interceptor method in the chain causes the target instance to be created.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="j">
            <text>Interceptor methods must always call the |InvocationContext.proceed| method or no subsequent interceptor methods, target class method, or lifecycle callback methods will be invoked, or the target instance will not be created.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="k">
            <text>If a method is of type void, the invocation of the |proceed| method returns |null|.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="l">
            <text>For all other lifecycle callback interceptor methods, if there is no callback method defined on the target class, the invocation of proceed in the last interceptor method in the chain is a no-op, and null is returned.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="m">
            <text>In case of the |PostConstruct| interceptor, if there is no callback method defined on the target class, the invocation of |InvocationContext.proceed| method in the last interceptor method in the chain validates the target instance.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.4" title="Exceptions">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>Interceptor methods are allowed to throw runtime exceptions or any checked exceptions that the associated target method allows within its throws clause.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>Interceptor methods are allowed to catch and suppress exceptions and to recover by calling the |InvocationContext.proceed| method.</text>
            <assertion id="ba">
                <text>Interceptor method is allowed to catch and suppress exceptions.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="bb">
                <text>Interceptor method is allowed to recover by calling the |InvocationContext.proceed| method.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>The invocation of the |InvocationContext.proceed| method will throw the same exception as any thrown by the associated target method unless an interceptor further down the Java call stack has caught it and thrown a different exception.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d" testable="false">
            <text>Exceptions and initialization and/or cleanup operations should typically be handled in try/catch/finally blocks around the proceed method.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.5" title="Business Method Interceptors">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>Interceptor methods that interpose on business method invocations are denoted by the |AroundInvoke| annotation.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>Around-invoke methods may be defined on interceptor classes and/or the target class and/or superclasses of the target class or the interceptor classes. However, only one around-invoke method may be defined on a given class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>Around-invoke methods can have |public|, |private|, |protected|, or |package| level access.</text>
            <assertion id="ca">
                <text>Test |public| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="cb">
                <text>Test |private| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="cc">
                <text>Test |protected| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="cd">
                <text>Test |package| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="d" testable="false">
            <text>An around-invoke method must not be declared as |abstract|, |final| or |static|.</text>
            <note>INTERCEPTORS_SPEC-22</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>An around-invoke method can invoke any component or resource that the method it is intercepting can invoke.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f">
            <text>In general, an around-invoke method invocation occurs within the same transaction and security context as the method on which it is interposing. However, note that the transaction context may be changed by transactional interceptors in the invocation chain.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.6" title="Interceptors for Lifecycle Event Callbacks">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>The |AroundConstruct| annotation denotes lifecycle callback interceptor methods that interpose on invocation of the target instance’s constructor.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>The |PostConstruct| annotation denotes lifecycle callback interceptor methods that are invoked after the target instance has been constructed and dependency injection on that instance has been completed, but before any business method or other event can be invoked on the target instance.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>The |PreDestroy| annotation denotes lifecycle callback interceptor methods that interpose on the target instance’s removal.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>The |AroundConstruct| interceptor methods may be only defined on interceptor classes and/or superclasses of interceptor classes. The |AroundConstruct| callback should not be defined on the target class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>All other interceptor methods that interpose on the target instance lifecycle event callbacks can be defined on an interceptor class and/or directly on the target class.</text>
            <assertion id="ea">
                <text>Test |PostConstruct| interceptor method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="eb">
                <text>Test |PreDestroy| interceptor method.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="f">
            <text>A single lifecycle callback interceptor method may be used to interpose on multiple callback events.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="g" testable="false">
            <text>Lifecycle callback interceptor methods are invoked in an unspecified security context.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="h">
            <text>Lifecycle callback interceptor methods are invoked in a transaction context determined by their target class and/or method.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="i">
            <text>|AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptor methods may be defined on superclasses of interceptor classes. All other lifecycle callback interceptor methods may be defined on superclasses of the target class or of interceptor classes. However, a given class may not have more than one lifecycle callback interceptor method for the same lifecycle event. Any subset or combination of lifecycle callback annotations may otherwise be specified on a target class or interceptor class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>Lifecycle callback interceptor methods can have |public|, |private|, |protected|, or |package| level access.</text>
            <assertion id="ja">
                <text>Test |public| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="jb">
                <text>Test |private| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="jc">
                <text>Test |protected| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="jd">
                <text>Test |package| level access.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="k" testable="false">
            <text>A lifecycle callback interceptor method must not be declared as |abstract|, |final| or |static|.</text>
            <note>INTERCEPTORS_SPEC-22</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.6.1" title="Exceptions">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>Lifecycle callback interceptor methods may throw runtime exceptions, but not checked exceptions.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>A lifecycle callback interceptor method (other than a method on the target class or its superclasses) may catch an exception thrown by another lifecycle callback interceptor method in the invocation chain, and clean up before returning.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>The |PreDestroy| callbacks are not invoked when the target instance and the interceptors are discarded as a result of such exceptions: the lifecycle callback interceptor methods in the chain should perform any necessary clean-up operations as the interceptor chain unwinds.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.7" title="Timeout Method Interceptors">

        <assertion id="a" testable="false">
            <text>Interceptor methods that interpose on timeout methods are denoted by the |AroundTimeout| annotation.</text>
            <note>Tested within the CDI TCK, 7.2 Container invocations and interception.</note>
        </assertion>

		<group>
		    <text>Around-timeout methods may be defined on interceptor classes and/or the target class and/or superclasses of the target class or interceptor classes. However, only one around-timeout method may be defined on a given class.</text>
			<assertion id="ba">
        		<text>Test interceptor classes and/or superclasses.</text>
        		<note>Partially tested within the CDI TCK, 7.2 Container invocations and interception.</note>
        	</assertion>
        	<assertion id="bb">
        		<text>Test target class and/or superclasses.</text>
        	</assertion>
		</group>

        <assertion id="c" testable="false">
            <text>Around-timeout methods can have |public|, |private|, |protected|, or |package| level access. An around-timeout method must not be declared as |abstract|, |final| or |static|.</text>
            <note>INTERCEPTORS_SPEC-22</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>An around-timeout method can invoke any component or resource that its corresponding timeout method can invoke.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>An around-timeout method invocation occurs within the same transaction and security context as the timeout method on which it is interposing.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f">
            <text>The |InvocationContext.getTimer| method allows an around-timeout method to retrieve the timer object associated with the timeout.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="2.8" title="Constructor- and Method-level Interceptors">

        <assertion id="aa">
            <text>Method-level interceptors are interceptor classes associated with a specific business or timeout method of the target class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="ab">
            <text>Constructor-level interceptors are interceptor classes associated with a constructor of the target class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>Only the interceptor methods of the interceptor class that are relevant for the context in which the interceptor is bound are invoked. For example, if the interceptor is bound only to a business method, any |AroundConstruct|, |AroundTimeout|, |PostConstruct|, or |PreDestroy| methods on the interceptor are not called.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c" testable="false">
            <text>Method-level interceptors may not be associated with a lifecycle callback method of the target class.</text>
            <note>INTERCEPTORS_SPEC-22</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>The same interceptor may be applied to more than one business or timeout method of the target class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>The applicability of a method-level interceptor to more than one method of an associated target class does not affect the relationship between the interceptor instance and the target class-only a single instance of the interceptor class is created per target class instance.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3" title="Associating Interceptors using Interceptor Bindings">

        <assertion id="a" testable="false">
            <text>Interceptor bindings are intermediate annotations that may be used to associate interceptors with any component that is not itself an interceptor.</text>
            <note>Statement of intent</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3.1" title="Interceptor Binding Types">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>An interceptor binding type is a Java annotation defined as |Retention(RUNTIME)|. Typically an interceptor binding is defined as |Target({TYPE, METHOD, CONSTRUCTOR})| or any subset of valid target types.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>An interceptor binding type may be declared by specifying the |InterceptorBinding| meta-annotation.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3.1.1"
        title="Interceptor binding types with additional interceptor bindings">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>An interceptor binding type may declare other interceptor bindings.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>Interceptor bindings are transitive — an interceptor binding declared by an interceptor binding type is inherited by all components and other interceptor binding types that declare that interceptor binding type.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>An interceptor binding type can only be applied to an interceptor binding type defining a superset of it's target types. For example interceptor binding types declared |Target(TYPE)| may not be applied to interceptor binding types declared |Target({TYPE, METHOD})|.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3.1.2" title="Other sources of interceptor bindings">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>An extension specification may define other sources of interceptor bindings, such as via a CDI stereotype.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3.2" title="Declaring Interceptor Bindings of an Interceptor">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>The interceptor bindings of an interceptor are specified by annotating the interceptor class with the binding types and the |Interceptor| annotation and are called the set of interceptor bindings for the interceptor.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>An interceptor class may declare multiple interceptor bindings.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>Multiple interceptors may declare the same interceptor bindings.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>An extension specification may define other ways of declaring an interceptor.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>If an interceptor does not declare an |Interceptor| annotation, it could be bound to components using |Interceptors| annotation or a deployment descriptor file.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f" testable="false">
            <text>All interceptors declared using the |Interceptor| annotation should specify at least one interceptor binding. If an interceptor declared using the |Interceptor| annotation does not declare any interceptor binding, non-portable behavior results.</text>
            <note>Non-portable mode</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="g">
            <text>With the exception of |AroundConstruct| lifecycle callback interceptors, an interceptor for lifecycle callbacks may only declare interceptor binding types that are defined as |Target(TYPE)|.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3.3" title="Binding an Interceptor to a Component">

        <group>
            <text>An interceptor may be bound to a component by annotating the component class, a method, or constructor of the component class, with the interceptor binding type.</text>
            <assertion id="aa">
                <text>Test a component class.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="ab">
                <text>Test a method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="ac">
                <text>Test a constructor.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <group>
            <text>A component class, method, or constructor of a component class may declare multiple interceptor bindings.</text>
            <assertion id="ba">
                <text>Test a component class.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="bb">
                <text>Test a method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="bc">
                <text>Test a constructor.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>The set of interceptor bindings for a method or constructor are those declared at class level combined with those declared at method or constructor level.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>An interceptor binding declared on a method or constructor replaces an interceptor binding of the same type declared at class level or inherited from a superclass.</text>
            <assertion id="da">
                <text>Test a constructor.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="db">
                <text>Test a method.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>An extension specification may define additional rules for combining interceptor bindings, such as interceptors defined via a CDI stereotype.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f" testable="false">
            <text>If the component class declares or inherits a class level interceptor binding, it must not be declared |final|, or have any non-|static|, non-|private|, |final| methods. If a component has a class-level interceptor binding and is declared |final| or has a non-|static|, non-|private|, |final| method, the container automatically detects the problem and treats it as a definition error.</text>
            <note>Tested within the CDI TCK, 9.3 Binding an interceptor to a bean.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="g" testable="false">
            <text>If a non-|static|, non-|private| method of a component class declares a method level interceptor binding, neither the method nor the component class may be declared |final|. If a non-|static|, non-|private|, |final| method of a component has a method level interceptor binding, the container automatically detects the problem and treats it as a definition error.</text>
            <note>Tested within the CDI TCK, 9.3 Binding an interceptor to a bean.</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3.4" title="Interceptor Resolution">

        <assertion id="a" testable="false">
            <text>The process of matching interceptors to a certain lifecycle callback method, timeout method, business method or a constructor of a certain component is called interceptor resolution.</text>
            <note>Statement of intent</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>For a lifecycle callback, the interceptor bindings include the interceptor bindings declared or inherited by the component at the class level, including, recursively, interceptor bindings declared as meta-annotations of other interceptor bindings.</text>
        </assertion>

        <group>
            <text>For a business method, timeout method, or constructor the interceptor bindings include the interceptor bindings declared or inherited by the component at the class level, including, recursively, interceptor bindings declared as meta-annotations of other interceptor bindings, together with all interceptor bindings declared on the constructor or method, including, recursively, interceptor bindings declared as meta-annotations of other interceptor bindings.</text>
            <assertion id="ca">
                <text>Test a business method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="cb">
                <text>Test a timeout method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="cc">
                <text>Test a constructor.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <group>
            <text>An interceptor is bound to a method or constructor if:</text>
            <assertion id="da">
                <text>The method or constructor has all the interceptor bindings of the interceptor. A method or constructor has an interceptor binding of an interceptor if it has an interceptor binding with (a) the same type and (b) the same annotation member value for each member. An extension specification may further refine this rule. For example the CDI specification adds the |javax.enterprise.util.Nonbinding| annotation, causing member values to be ignored by the resolution process.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="db">
                <text>The interceptor intercepts the given kind of lifecycle callback or business method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="dc">
                <text>The interceptor is enabled.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

    </section>

    <section id="3.4.1" title="Interceptors with multiple bindings">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>An interceptor class may specify multiple interceptor bindings.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="3.4.2" title="Interceptor binding types with members">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>Interceptor binding types may have annotation members.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b">
            <text>Annotation member values are compared using the equals method.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c">
            <text>Array-valued or annotation-valued members of an interceptor binding type are not supported. An extension specification may add support for these member types. For example the CDI specification adds the |javax.enterprise.util.Nonbinding| annotation, allowing array-valued or annotation-valued members to be used on the annotation type, but ignored by the resolution process.</text>
            <note>Testing |javax.enterprise.util.Nonbinding| annotation.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>If the set of interceptor bindings of a component class or interceptor, including bindings inherited from stereotypes and other interceptor bindings, has two instances of a certain interceptor binding type and the instances have different values of some annotation member, the container automatically detects the problem and treats it as a definition error.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="4"
        title="Associating Interceptors using the Interceptors Annotation">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>The |Interceptors| annotation can be used to denote interceptor classes and associate one or more interceptor classes with a target class, and/or one or more of its methods, and/or a constructor of the target class.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b" testable="false">
            <text>If multiple interceptors are defined for the target class in the Interceptors annotation, they are invoked in the order in which they are specified. See Chapter 5 for the rules on interceptors ordering.</text>
            <note>Tested in section 5.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c" testable="false">
            <text>If a deployment descriptor is supported, it can be used to associate interceptor classes with the target class, and/or methods, and/or a constructor of the target class and specify the order of interceptor invocation or override metadata specified by annotations.</text>
            <note>Should be tested in the EJB TCK.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>Method-level around-invoke and around-timeout interceptors can be defined by applying the |Interceptors| annotation to the method for which the interceptors are to be invoked.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="e">
            <text>Constructor-level interceptors can be defined by applying the |Interceptors| annotation to the constructor for which the interceptors are to be invoked.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="f" testable="false">
            <text>If more than one constructor- or method-level interceptor is defined for a target class constructor or method, the interceptors are invoked in the order specified. Constructor- and method-level interceptors are invoked in addition to any default interceptors and interceptors defined for the target class (and its superclasses).</text>
            <note>Tested in section 5.</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="4.1" title="Default Interceptors">

        <assertion id="a" testable="false">
            <text>Default interceptors are interceptors that apply to a set of target classes. If a deployment descriptor is supported, it may be used to define default interceptors and their relative ordering.</text>
            <note>Should be tested in the EJB TCK.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b" testable="false">
            <text>The |ExcludeDefaultInterceptors| annotation is used to exclude the invocation of default interceptors for a target class, or when applied to a target class constructor or method, is used to exclude the invocation of default interceptors for that constructor or that method.</text>
            <note>Should be tested in the EJB TCK.</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="5" title="Interceptor Ordering">
    </section>

    <section id="5.1" title="Defining Interceptor Order">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>Associating interceptors with the target class or method of the target class using the |Interceptors| annotation enables them for the target class, a method, or a constructor of the target class. The order in which they are invoked is determined by the order in which they are specified in the annotation.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b" testable="false">
            <text>Interceptors declared using interceptor bindings are enabled and ordered using the |Priority| annotation or the beans.xml deployment descriptor.</text>
            <note>Tested within the CDI TCK, section 9.4 Interceptor enablement and ordering.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c" testable="false">
            <text>An extension specification may define alternative mechanisms to enable and order interceptors.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d" testable="false">
            <text>For the same interceptor method type, interceptors declared using interceptor bindings are called after interceptors declared using the |Interceptors| annotation (or using the corresponding element of a deployment descriptor) and before an interceptor method of the same interceptor type declared on the target class or any superclass of the target class.</text>
           	<note>Tested within the CDI TCK, section 9.4 Interceptor enablement and ordering.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion testable="false">
            <text>The |InvocationContext| object enables interceptor methods to control the behavior of the invocation chain, including whether the next method in the chain is invoked and the values of its parameters and result.</text>
            <note>Tested in section 2.3</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="5.2" title="Common Ordering Rules"></section>

    <section id="5.2.1"
        title="Invocation Order of Interceptors Declared on the Target Class">

        <group>
            <text>Interceptor methods declared on the target class or its superclasses are invoked in the following order:</text>
            <assertion id="aa">
                <text>If a target class has superclasses, any interceptor methods defined on those superclasses are invoked, most general superclass first.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="ab">
                <text>The interceptor method, if any, on the target class itself is invoked.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <group>
            <text>If an interceptor method is overridden by another method (regardless of whether that method is itself an interceptor method), it will not be invoked.</text>
            <assertion id="ba">
                <text>Test business method interceptor method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="bb">
                <text>Test lifecycle interceptor method.</text>
            </assertion>
        </group>

    </section>

    <section id="5.2.2" title="Invocation Order of Interceptors with Superclasses">

        <assertion id="a">
            <text>If an interceptor class itself has superclasses, the interceptor methods defined by the interceptor class’s superclasses are invoked before the interceptor method defined by the interceptor class, most general superclass first.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="5.3" title="Ordering Interceptors using the Priority Annotation">

        <assertion id="a" testable="false">
            <text>An interceptor bound to a component, a component method, or constructor using interceptor binding may be enabled for the entire application by applying the |Priority| annotation, along with a priority value, on the interceptor class.</text>
            <note>Tested within the CDI TCK, section 9.4 Interceptor enablement and ordering.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="b" testable="false">
            <text>Interceptors with smaller priority values are called first.</text>
            <note>Tested within the CDI TCK, section 9.4 Interceptor enablement and ordering.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="c" testable="false">
            <text>If more than one interceptor has the same priority, the relative order of these interceptor is undefined.</text>
            <note>Undefined behaviour.</note>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="d">
            <text>The |Priority| annotation is ignored on interceptors bound to a component using the |Interceptors| annotation.</text>
        </assertion>

        <assertion id="e" testable="false">
            <text>Extension specifications may define other ways of assigning priorities to an interceptor.</text>
            <note>CDI does not define other way of assigning priorities.</note>
        </assertion>

    </section>

    <section id="5.4" title="Interceptor Priority"></section>

    <section id="5.5"
        title="Invocation Order for Multiple Interceptors Defined Using the Interceptors Annotation">

        <group>
            <text>If multiple business or timeout method interceptor methods are defined for a target class or multiple callback interceptor methods are defined for a lifecycle event for a target class using the Interceptors annotation, the following rules govern their invocation order for each interceptor type. A deployment descriptor may be used to override the interceptor invocation order specified in annotations.</text>
            <assertion id="a" testable="false">
                <text>Default interceptors, if any, are invoked first. Default interceptors can only be specified in a deployment descriptor. Default interceptors are invoked in the order of their specification in the deployment descriptor.</text>
                <note>Should be tested in the EJB TCK.</note>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="b">
                <text>If there are any interceptor classes associated with the target class using the |Interceptors| annotation, the interceptor methods defined by those interceptor classes are invoked before any interceptor methods defined on the target class itself.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="c">
                <text>The interceptor methods defined on those interceptor classes are invoked in the same order as the specification of the interceptor classes in the |Interceptors| annotation.
                </text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="d" testable="false">
                <text>If an interceptor class itself has superclasses, the interceptor methods are invoked according to the rules described in the section 5.2.2.</text>
                <note>Tested in 5.2.2</note>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="e">
                <text>After the interceptor methods defined on interceptor classes have been invoked, then if any constructor- or around-invoke or around-timeout method-level interceptors are defined for the target class constructor or method that is to be invoked, the corresponding methods defined on those interceptor classes are invoked in the same order as the specification of those interceptor classes in the Interceptors annotation applied to that target class constructor or method.</text>
            </assertion>
            <assertion id="f" testable="false">
                <text>And then interceptors declared on the target class or its superclasses are invoked according to the rules described in the section 5.2.1.</text>
                <note>Tested in 5.2.1</note>
            </assertion>
        </group>

        <assertion id="g">
            <text>The |ExcludeClassInterceptors| annotation can be used to exclude the invocation of the class-level interceptors.</text>
        </assertion>

    </section>

</specification>
