<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="executing-test-harness">
   <title>Executing a Test Suite</title>
   <para>
      This chapter explains how to execute and debug a test suite built using
      the JBoss Test Harness.
   </para>
   <section id="test-suite-runner">
      <title>Building a test suite runner using Maven 2</title>
      <para>
         The test suite runner project is the magic that makes everything come
         together and allows you to execute the test suite. If you fully
         understand how the JBoss Test Harness functions, and have a good grasp
         on Maven 2, then it's not to difficult to understand how the test suite
         runner project works. Regardless of your background, this guide covers
         what you need to know to get up and running by studying the test suite
         runner used to run the CDI TCK against the CDI RI, Weld.
      </para>
      <para>
         The TCK runner for the Weld can be found in the jboss-tck-runner
         directory in the Weld distribution. The dependencies of the TCK
         runner project for Weld are listed in
         <xref linkend="tck-runner-dependencies" />. You must also pull in
         the transitive dependencies of these projects.
      </para>
      <table frame="all" id="tck-runner-dependencies" title="CDI TCK Runner dependencies">
         <title>Weld JBoss TCK Runner Dependencies</title>
         <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colname="c1" />
            <colspec colname="c2" />
            <colspec colname="c3" />
            <thead>
               <row>
                  <entry>Group ID</entry>
                  <entry>Artifact ID</entry>
                  <entry>Version</entry>
               </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry>javax.enterprise</entry>
                  <entry>cdi-api</entry>
                  <entry>1.0.X-Q</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>org.jboss.jsr299.tck</entry>
                  <entry>jsr299-tck-api</entry>
                  <entry>1.0.X-Q</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>org.jboss.jsr299.tck</entry>
                  <entry>jsr299-tck-impl</entry>
                  <entry>1.0.X-Q</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>org.jboss.weld</entry>
                  <entry>weld-core</entry>
                  <entry>1.Y.Z-R</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>org.jboss.weld</entry>
                  <entry>weld-porting-package</entry>
                  <entry>1.Y.Z-R</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>org.testng</entry>
                  <entry>testng (classifier: jdk15)</entry>
                  <entry>5.10</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry>org.jboss.test-harness</entry>
                  <entry>jboss-test-harness-jboss-as-52</entry>
                  <entry>1.1.0-CR2</entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
         You can find all of the CDI API and TCK in Maven Central and JBoss Test Harness in the <ulink
         url="http://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/">JBoss Maven
         repository</ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
         You should substitute the weld-core and weld-porting-package
         artifacts from table 2.2.3 with your own artifacts. You'll also need to
         replace the jboss-test-harness-jboss-as-52 artifact if you are not
         testing your implementation on JBoss AS 6.0. The
         jboss-test-harness-jboss-as-52 artifact contains implementations of the
         <literal>Containers</literal>
         SPI for the JBoss Test Harness for JBoss AS 6.0.
      </para>
      <note>
         <para>
            When running the test suite in the in-container mode, the tests
            will run against libraries installed into the container. In this
            project, Weld is only declared as a Maven dependency for when
            the TCK test suite is being executed in standalone mode.
         </para>
      </note>

      <programlisting role="xml"><![CDATA[<plugin>
  <groupId>org.apache.maven.plugins</groupId>
  <artifactId>maven-dependency-plugin</artifactId>
  <executions>
    <execution>
      <id>copy</id>
      <phase>process-resources</phase>
      <goals>
        <goal>copy</goal>
      </goals>
      <configuration>
        <stripVersion>true</stripVersion>
        <artifactItems>
          <artifactItem>
            <groupId>org.jboss.jsr299.tck</groupId>
            <artifactId>jsr299-tck-impl</artifactId>
            <type>xml</type>
            <classifier>suite</classifier>
            <overWrite>true</overWrite>
          </artifactItem>
          <artifactItem>
            <groupId>org.jboss.weld</groupId>
            <artifactId>
              weld-porting-package
            </artifactId>
            <overWrite>true</overWrite>
            <outputDirectory>
              ${project.build.directory}/dependency/lib
            </outputDirectory>
          </artifactItem>
          <artifactItem>
            <groupId>org.jboss.weld</groupId>
            <artifactId>weld-core-test</artifactId>
            <overWrite>true</overWrite>
            <outputDirectory>
              ${project.build.directory}/dependency/lib
            </outputDirectory>
          </artifactItem>
          <artifactItem>
            <groupId>javax.el</groupId>
            <artifactId>el-ri</artifactId>
            <overWrite>true</overWrite>
            <outputDirectory>
              ${project.build.directory}/dependency/lib
            </outputDirectory>
            </artifactItem>
          </artifactItems>
       </configuration>
     </execution>
   </executions>
</plugin>]]></programlisting>
      <para>
         The target folder for the copies of the dependencies (i.e., the JAR
         files) is declared as the JBoss Test Harness library directory; this
         results in these libraries being added to the test artifact using the
         following property assignment:
      </para>
      <programlisting>org.jboss.testharness.libraryDirectory=target/dependency/lib</programlisting>
      <para>
         We also copy the test suite configuration from the
         local Maven
         repository (groupId=org.jboss.jsr299.tck,
         artifactId=jsr299-tck-impl,
         classifier=suite, type=xml,
         version=1.0.0-SNAPSHOT) to a local
         repository as the TestNG Maven
         plugin expects a local file.
      </para>
      <para>
         The TCK is executed using the Maven TestNG plugin. Maven 2 profiles are
         used to control the properties that are set at the time of the
         execution. For instance, the
         <literal>incontainer</literal>
         profile enables integration tests and disables standalone mode,
         changing the default settings.
      </para>
      <para>
         The jboss-tck-runner project also defines the JBoss Test Harness
         extra configuration directory using the following property:
      </para>
      <programlisting>org.jboss.testharness.container.extraConfigurationDir=../jboss-as</programlisting>
      <para>
         The JBoss Test Harness looks in this directory for either a
         build.properties or local.build.properties file that declares
         additional configuration properties. In particular, the JBoss AS
         Containers implementation looks here to find the
         <literal>jboss.home</literal> property so it knows where the scripts
         are located to start and stop JBoss AS.
      </para>
   </section>

   <section id="dumping-test-artifacts">
      <title>Dumping the Test Artifacts to Disk</title>
      <para>
         As you have learned, when the test suite is executing using
         in-container mode, each test class is packaged as a deployable artifact
         and deployed to the container. The test is then executed within the
         context of the deployed application. This leaves room for errors in
         packaging. When investigating a test failure, it's helpful to be able
         to inspect the artifact after it is generated. The JBoss Test Harness
         can accommodate this type of inspection by "dumping" the generated
         artifact to disk.
      </para>
      <para>
         If you want to write the artifacts to disk, and avoid executing the
         test suite, you can simply execute the main method of the class
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.api.TCK</literal>.
         For example you could use a Maven profile that is activated when the
         <literal>dumpArtifacts</literal>
         command line property is defined:
      </para>
      <programlisting>mvn test-compile -DdumpArtifacts</programlisting>
      <para>
         The output directory where the artifacts are written is defined by the
         property
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.outputDirectory</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
         Once the artifact is written to disk, you have an option of manually
         deploying it to the container. You can execute the tests in the artifact
         by requesting the context path of the application in the browser. If
         you want to execute an individual test method, specify the method name
         in the
         <literal>methodName</literal>
         request parameter (e.g., ?methodName=testMethodName).
      </para>
   </section>
</chapter>
