<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [ ]>
<chapter id="test-harness-introduction">
   <title>Introduction (JBoss Test Harness)</title>

   <para>
      This chapter explains the purpose of the test harness and describes
      its key features.
   </para>
   <para>
      The JBoss Test Harness is a testing framework based on TestNG that
      provides a series of extensions that allow runtime packaging and
      deployment of Java EE artifacts (EAR or WAR) for in-container testing.
      It's important to note that the JBoss Test Harness has no relation with,
      or dependency on, the JBoss Application Server (JBoss AS).
   </para>
   <note>
      <para>
         You'll often see the term
         <emphasis role="italic">in-container</emphasis>
         used in this reference guide. This term refers to running the test
         suite in any of the aforementioned environments, whilst
         <emphasis role="italic">standalone</emphasis>
         refers to running the tests outside the container via an
         implementation-specific standalone bootstrap. The standalone mode only
         runs those tests which the CDI RI can run without deployment in a Java
         EE container.
      </para>
   </note>
   <para>
      The last thing Java developers want is yet another testing framework to
      make their life more complicated. That's why the JBoss Test Harness is
      built entirely upon TestNG. TestNG is one of two prominent test
      frameworks for Java (the other being JUnit). Furthermore, what developers
      want is a good integration with their Integrated Development Environment
      (IDE). These days, if a tool doesn't have an IDE plugin, then it won't
      get the attention it deserves. TestNG plugins are available for all major
      IDEs and build tools (Ant and Maven 2). Again, a motivating factor for
      extending TestNG.
   </para>
   <para>
      Because it leverages the existing TestNG ecosystem, there is no need for
      a special test launcher for the JBoss Test Harness. You simply use the
      IDE or build tool of your choice (so long as it has TestNG support). You
      also get reporting and debugging for free (various reporting plugins are
      provided for TestNG).
   </para>
   <para>
      You can read more about TestNG at
      <ulink url="http://testng.org/doc/documentation-main.html">testng.org</ulink>.
   </para>
   <para>
      The JBoss Test Harness supports the following features:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Test activation via any method supported by the TestNG
            configuration descriptor (package, group, class)
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Exclusion of in-container tests in standalone mode
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Exclusion of individual tests labeled as under investigation
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Integration with any TestNG plugin (Eclipse, IntelliJ, Ant, Maven)
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Automated reporting capability as provided by TestNG
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Standalone and in-container test mode
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Container pluggability
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Declarative packaging of additional resources and classes in
            artifact
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Declarative deployment exception trapping
         </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
         <para>
            Artifact dumping for failure and packaging analysis
         </para>
      </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
      A test is designated by a method annotated with
      <literal>@org.testng.annotations.Test</literal>
      in a class which extends
      <literal>org.jboss.testharness.AbstractTest</literal>
      and is annotated with
      <literal>@org.jboss.testharness.impl.packaging.Artifact</literal>.
   </para>
   <note>
      <para>
         Test suites may often choose to extend <literal>AbstractTest</literal>
         and require tests to extend that base class. In fact, both the CDI TCK
         and the Bean Validation TCK provide base classes that extend
         <literal>AbstractTest</literal> to provide functionality specific to
         the needs of the TCK.
      </para>
   </note>
   <para>
      The
      <literal>@Test</literal>
      annotation is provided by TestNG, the
      <literal>@Artifact</literal>
      annotation is provided by the JBoss Test Harness and the
      <literal>AbstractTest</literal>
      is part of the JBoss Test Harness. There is a one-to-one mapping between a
      TestNG test class and an artifact. The packaging type is defined by the
      <literal>@org.jboss.testharness.impl.packaging.Packaging</literal>
      annotation on the test class, defaulting to a WAR if not specified.
   </para>
   <para>
      Prior to executing the tests for a given class, the JBoss Test Harness
      packages the class as a deployable artifact (EAR or WAR), along with any
      extra resources specified, and deploys the artifact to the container. The
      harness provides test execution and result reporting via HTTP
      communication to a simple Servlet using a thin layer over the TestNG test
      launcher. The test harness can also catch and enforce expected deployment
      exceptions. This setup and tear down activity is provided by the super
      class
      <literal>org.jboss.testharness.AbstractTest</literal>,
      which all test classes must extend (directly or indirectly).
   </para>
   <para>
      If the annotation
      <literal>@org.jboss.testharness.impl.packaging.IntegrationTest
      </literal>
      is not present on the test class, then it means the test class can be
      executed in standalone mode. In standalone mode, the deployable artifact
      is assembled on the local classpath and the tests execute in the same JVM
      as the launcher, just as though it were a regular TestNG test case. The
      standalone mode is provided for convenience and efficiency, allowing you
      the speed of mock-based testing and the confidence of an in-container test,
      using the same test objects and tests.
   </para>
   
      <section id="in-container-communication">
      <title>Negotiating the execution of an in-container test</title>
      <para>
         The basic procedure of an in-container test is as follows. The JBoss
         Test Harness produces a deployable artifact from an
         <literal>@Artifact</literal>
         test class and any declared dependent classes, descriptors or other
         resources. Then it deploys the artifact to the container using the
         <literal>Containers</literal>
         SPI, negotiates with the container to execute the test and return the
         result and, finally, undeploys the artifact. TestNG collects the results
         of all the tests run in the typical way and produces a report.
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/in-container-execution.png" align="center" />
      <para>
         The question is, how does the JBoss Test Harness negotiate with the
         container to execute the test when TestNG is being invoked locally?
         Technically the mechanism is pluggable, but JBoss Test Harness provides
         a default implementation that uses HTTP communication that you will
         likely use. Here's how the default implementation works.
      </para>
      <para>
         The artifact generator bundles and registers (in the web.xml
         descriptor) an
         <literal>HttpServlet</literal>,
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.impl.runner.servlet.ServletTestRunner</literal>,
         that responds to test execution GET requests. TestNG running on the
         client side delegates to a test launcher (more on that in a moment)
         which originates these text execution requests to transfer control to
         the container JVM. The name of the test method to be executed is
         specified in a request query parameter named
         <literal>methodName</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
         When the test execution request is received, the servlet delegates to
         an instance of
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.impl.runner.TestRunner</literal>,
         passing it the name of the test method.
         <literal>TestRunner</literal>
         reads the name of the test class from the resource
         META-INF/jboss-test-harness.properties, which is bundled in the
         artifact by the artifact generator. It then combines the class name
         and the method name to produce a TestNG test suite and runs the suite
         (within the context of the container).
      </para>
      <para>
         TestNG returns the results of the run as an
         <literal>ITestResult</literal>
         object.
         <literal>ServletTestRunner</literal>
         translates this object into a
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.api.TestResult</literal>
         and passes it back to the test launcher on the client side by encoding
         the translated object into the response. The object gets encoded as
         either html or a serialized object, depending on the value of the
         <literal>outputMode</literal>
         request parameter that was passed to the servlet. Once the result has
         been transferred to the client-side TestNG, TestNG wraps up the run of
         the test as though it had been executed in the same JVM.
      </para>
      <para>
         There's one piece missing. How does TestNG on the client side know to
         submit a request to the
         <literal>ServletTestRunner</literal>
         servlet to get TestNG to execute the test in the container JVM? That's
         the role of the test launcher.
      </para>
      <para>
         The test launcher is the API that allows test suite to launch the test
         in a pluggable fashion.
         <literal>AbstractTest</literal>,
         the super class of
         <literal>AbtractJSR299Test</literal>,
         implements
         <literal>IHookable</literal>,
         a TestNG interface which allows the execution of the test method to
         be intercepted. Using that mechanism, <literal>AbstractTest</literal> delegates execution
         of the test method (a method annotated with
         <literal>@Test</literal>
         in an
         <literal>@Artifact</literal>
         class) to an implementation of
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.api.TestLauncher</literal>
         if the tests are being executed in-container. As you might anticipate,
         the implementation is specified using a property with the same name as
         the interface in a META-INF/jboss-test-launcher.properties resource.
         The JBoss Test Harness provides a default implementation,
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.impl.runner.servlet.ServletTestLauncher</literal>,
         that hooks into the HTTP communication infrastructure described
         above. It invokes the
         <literal>ServletTestRunner</literal>
         servlet for each method annotated with
         <literal>@Test</literal>
         in the
         <literal>@Artifact</literal>
         that is not otherwise disabled.
      </para>
      <para>
         If you wish to implement the runner yourself, you must return a
         <literal>TestResult</literal> as a result of executing the method in
         the container. You must also ensure that any exception which occurs
         during deployment is wrapped as a
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.api.DeploymentException</literal>, and
         that any communication problem is rethrown as an
         <literal>IOException</literal>.  The deployment exception may be
         transformed by an implementation of the
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.api.DeploymentExceptionTransformer
         </literal> interface, which is specified using the
         <literal>org.jboss.testharness.container.deploymentExceptionTransformer
         </literal> property. The default implementation passes on the original
         exception unchanged. The implementation for JBoss AS used with the CDI
         TCK, on the other hand, deciphers the exception thrown by the JBoss
         deployer and converts it to one of the category exceptions defined in
         the CDI TCK API.
      </para>
      <para>
         So in short, JBoss Test Harness takes care of all the interfaces you
         need to execute tests in-container except for the implementation of
         the <literal>Containers</literal> SPI. That is, unless you are
         deploying to one of the containers supported by the JBoss Test Harness.
      </para>
   </section>
</chapter>
